Finding Aid for the Brian Urquhart Collection of Material about Ralph Bunche, ca. 1932-1972
UCLA Library Special Collections
Brian Urquhart Collection of Material about Ralph Bunche
ca. 1932-1972
364
UCLA Library Special Collections
24.0 linear ft. (48 boxes and 2 oversize boxes)
Sir Brian Urquhart (b.1919) was active in the organization and direction of the United Nations (UN) Emergency Force in Middle East (1956) and responsible for the organization and direction of UN peace-keeping operations and special political assignments. Ralph Bunche (1904-1971) was the undersecretary for special political affairs at the UN (1958-67) and undersecretary general (1968). He was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1950. The collection consists of papers about and collected by Ralph J. Bunche and later used by Brian Urquhart to write Ralph Bunche: an American Life (1993). Items in the collection include manuscripts, notebooks, project files, audiotape recordings, clippings, travel photographs, and memorabilia.
Urquhart, Brian
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF. Advance notice is required for access to the collection. Please contact UCLA Library Special Collections for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Brian Urquhart, 1995.
Biography
With an extensive background with the United Nations, Sir Brian Urquhart became a central figure in debates over the future of the United Nations and the role of UN security forces in the post-Cold War era. Born in England in 1919, he was educated at Westminster School and Christ Church, Oxford University. After serving in the British army and military intelligence during World War II in North Africa and Europe, he served as a personal assistant to Gladwyn Jebb, who established the Preparatory Commission of the United Nations in London. From 1946 to 1949, he was personal assistant to the Trygve Lie, the first Secretary-General, and subsequently he served in various capacities under Ralph Bunche between 1954 and 1971. Over this period, Sir Brian was centrally involved in the conferences on peaceful uses of atomic energy, the Congo crisis in the early 1960s, and peacekeeping in Cyprus, Kashmir, and the Middle East. In the period after 1972, Brian Urquhart was one of the principal political advisors of the Secretary-General, and served as the Under-Secretary-General for Special Political Affairs, working on Lebanon, Israel and Palestine, and Namibia, among others. He retired from the United Nations Secretariat in 1986.
Urquhart has written several books, including biographies of Dag Hammarskjöld and Ralph Bunche; an autobiography, A Life in Peace and War; and books on decolonization and reforming the United Nations system. His continued involvement with the United Nations is also reflected in his pieces on the UN volunteer force and the responsibilities of the UN system published in The New York Review of Books in 1993 and 1994, as well as his involvement with the events surrounding the fiftieth UN anniversary.
Ralph J. Bunche (1904-1971) received his undergraduate degree from UCLA and his doctoral degree from Harvard and served as a professor at Howard University and at Harvard. He joined the Permanent Secretariat of the United Nations in 1948, served as the undersecretary for special political affairs from 1958 to 1967, and then became undersecretary general in 1968. In 1950, Bunche was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of papers about, and collected by Ralph J. Bunche and later used by his colleague and biographer, Brian Urquhart. Includes manuscripts, his notebooks, project files, audiotape recordings, clippings, travel photographs, and memorabilia. The notebooks document more than five decades of Bunche's evolution as a political thinker and carefully preserve the origin and genesis of his major published and unpublished speeches, essays, articles, and other writings. Project files include research materials consulted by Bunche, reports generated by him and/or his affiliates, and photocopies of business correspondence. Audiotapes include transcriptions of taped interviews with Bunche, mostly from the 1960s. Clippings and memorabilia include articles by and about Bunche, along with reviews and letters to him.
Related Material
Ralph J. Bunche Papers (Collection 2051). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233917
Bunche, Ralph J. (Ralph Johnson), 1904-1971.; United Nations--Officials and employees.; Urquhart, Brian--Archives.; Diplomats--Archives.
Container List
- General, Including Myrdal Study., 1932-1945.; [Box 1, 7 folders]
  - Photocopies and notes. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes:
    Photograph (photocopy) of R.J. Bunche, n.d.
  - R.J. Bunche handwritten notes., 1932, 1940, 1941. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content
    Photocopies of transcripts.
  - American race relations 1930-1947, Myrdal study. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1) Typescript (carbon) of letter from R.J. Bunche to Dr. Gunnar Myrdal, September 26, 1941.
    2) Photocopied material from Myrdal studies, correspondence.
  - Myrdal study., 1939: August-September. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1) Photocopy of R.J. Bunche's handwritten diary of trip to South with Gunnar Myrdal.
  - R.J. Bunche biographical information to 1943., 1925-1943. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1) Typescript (carbon) of R.J. Bunche's resumé, 1925-1943.
    2) R.J. Bunche's list of professional employment references, 1925-April 1945.
  - OSS - MT. Tremblant - Joined State Department January 1944 - Dumbarton Oaks., 1942-1945, 1982. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1) Photocopy of postwar foreign policy preparation, 1939-1945.
    2) Photocopy of UN Conference on International Organization, April 26, 1945.
  - R.J. Bunche notes September 18-November 10, 1945 - ILO Conference, London and Paris., 1945 March 13-December 27. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1) Photocopy of letters to and from Mrs. Roosevelt.
    2) Photocopies of letters to and from R.J. Bunche.
    3) Photocopies of UN Conference on International Delegation.
- London School of Economics; Africa Trip., 1932, 1937-1938.; [Boxes 1 and 2, 4 folders]
  - Original notes re: which boxes contain correspondence on R.J. Bunche's trip to Africa as well as quotes from those boxes., 1932-1938. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Also, photograph (photocopy) of R.J. Bunche and Dr. J. Gikonyo Kiano of Kenya.
  - R.J. Bunche's handwritten diaries., 1937.; (Photocopies) (Box 1-2)
    - ., 1937: January-July. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ., 1937: August-December. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ., 1938: January-November and 1939. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters to and from R.J. Bunche., November 2, 1938-May 23, 1939.; (Photocopies) (Box 2, Folder 1)
- OSS, State Department., 1941-1946.; [Box 2, 5 folders]
  - Letters between Brian Urquhart and Larry Finkelstein., 1982: March-April.; (1 photocopy and 2 originals) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Article by Finkelstein entitled, Castles in Spain--UN Arrangements for Postwar Colonial Progress. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between L.S. Finkelstein and Gaby Gervais, secretary of R.J. Bunche., July 11-18, 1969.; (Original and photocopied) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapter 5 of L.S. Finkelstein entitled, Trusteeship at San Francisco., 1941-1942. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Article by Dr. Conyers Read entitled, African Proposals. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - R.J. Bunche's notes on Read's African Proposals., (Typescript [carbon] and photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Article by Anson P. Stokes, The Atlantic Charter & Africa., (Photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 3 letters to and from J.A. Wilson., February 26, 1943-March January 1943.; (Photocopies) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Bunche's notes on Conyers Read., March 6, 1943.; (Photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Bunche's Psychological Warfare Roundup., April 1943.; (Photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Joint articles by R.J. Bunche and Sherman Kent., September 1943.; (photocopies) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Cordell Hull from Charles W. Taussig., June 2, 1944.; Photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letter to RJB from Anson Phelps-Stokes., Feb 15, 1944.; Photocopy.
- Companion Volume 1., 1940-1949.; [Box 2, 7 folders]
  - Notes re R.J. Bunche's trip to Africa., 1938: July, December. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    1) Photocopy of R.J. Bunche's handwritten diary December 23-31, 1938 and July 6-7, 1938.
    2) Photocopy of newspaper photograph of Dr. J.G. Kiano of Kenya with R.J. Bunche.
    3) Photocopy of part of article about R.J. Bunche's trip to Kenya from New York Herald.
  - Howard University's National Conference Program., May 18-20, 193[?]. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    1) Letter: R.J. Bunche to Max Yergan December 1938.
    2) Letter: R.J. Bunche to Malvina C. Thompson September 11, 1940.
  - Ralph Bunche: The Africanist by Nathan Irvin Huggins., May 5-6, 1986. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Article from Chicago Defender., January 18, 1941.; (Photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Original Bobbs-Merril reprint of R.J. Bunche's article, The Negro in the Political Life of the United States., July 1941. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Memo from E.R. Embree to W.C. Haygood., May 21, 1941.; (Photocopy) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters from Lewis Hanke to R.J. Bunche and from R.J. Bunche to L. Hanke., June 18, 1941 July 3, 1941.; (Photocopies) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - R.J. Bunche's employment., 1925-1945. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - R.J. Bunche's positions Department of State., 1941-1947. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Typed notes from R.J. Bunche's S. African diary., September 1941, December 1942, January 1943. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - J. Greene Interview., December 1985 and December 1982. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bernard Young Jr. article., 1945. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letter: Urquhart to Heyman., 1989. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper transcripts., April-May 1945. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - L.S. Finkelstein's Bunche and Colonial World: from Trusteeship to Decolonization (Essay) in Department of State Bulletin., December 1945. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - R.J. Bunche article: San Francisco conference and Colonial Issues., 1946. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letter: Adlai Stephenson to R.J. Bunche., 1945. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - R.J. Bunche's UN positions., 1946-1954. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Interview [with] Cleantho de Paiva Leite., 1989. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - San Francisco Conference on International Organization., 1945. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - R.J. Bunche's letters., May-November 1946.; (Typescript) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - R.J. Bunche's diary., May-December 1946.; (Typescript) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - List of R.J. Bunche's photos., March-December 1947. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Interviews,: William Mashier; Kenneth Dadzie; Mr. Shivashinka and Joan Liu (19??)., 1982. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Handwritten letter to Joan from Daddy., 1952. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Special Committee on Palestine: members, draft by Secretary General to Secretary. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - R.J. Bunche Photo list., 1948: January-November. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cable: R.J. Bunche to Azcarate., 1948. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Documents translated from English to French., 1948. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cable/letter: R.J. Bunche - MacDonald., 1948. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - R.J. Bunche's typed diary., October 1948. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cable: R.J. Bunche to Rhodes., October 1948. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typed notes on R.J. Bunche., October-December 1948. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cables: R.J. Bunche - Ahman/Reedman., December 1948. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Prospects for Peace in Palestine., December 1948. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Interviews: J.Reedman; Mishler., 1988. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - List of R.J. Bunche photos/articles., 1949. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters: Moshe Shertok - R.J. Bunche; Abaza - Ascarate; R.J. Bunche - Rosenne., 1949. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Notes on Trygve Lie. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cable: R.J. Bunche to Rhodes., 1949. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - R.J. Bunche typed diary., April-October 1949. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Essay: R.J. Bunche as UN Mediator by J.C. Hurewitz. (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Companion Volume 2., 1950-1967.; [Box 3, 4 folders]
  - List R.J. Bunche's University talks., January-December 1950. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - List R.J. Bunche photos/press clippings., 1950; 1951; 1953. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - R.J. Bunche's diary re: Nobel Prize trip., November-December 1950.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Typed notes: R.J. Bunche Conference., 1986. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Essay: National Secretary and Civil Rights: Case of R.J. Bunche by C.P. Henry., 1986. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - R.J. Bunche's diary., November 1953.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - List photos, typescript clippings., 1954-1958 1954-1958. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letter: Johnson - R.J. Bunche., November 1955. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notes: early UN Emergency Force Advisory Committee., 1956. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - R.J. Bunche diary., March 3-9, 1957.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Confidential memos: R.J. Bunche - Secretary General., October 1957. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - R.J. Bunche photos/press clippings., 1959-1961.; (List typescripts) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - R.J. Bunche diary., February 13, 1959; April 1959.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Cable: Von Horn - Secretary General., 1959. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jerusalem Post article on R.J. Bunche., 1959. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters: R.J. Bunche - Von Horn; Henry Vigier., 1959. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Press clippings., 1959 and 1960. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Written notes., 1959.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - R.J. Bunche itinerary., January 1960. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Interview: General Rikhye., 1959-1961. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - R.J. Bunche UN Press Releases., 1962.; (Original and copies) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Bunche photo/press clippings., 1962-1967.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 87th Congressional Record., 1962. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - UN Speech by acting Secretary General transcript., 1962. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Interview: Lieutenant General Pruchand. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notes: funeral for E. Roosevelt; UN Meeting; Vietnam., 1962 1965 1965. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Written notes., 1963.; (Typescript) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cables: R.J. Bunche - Van Horn/Cos/Bull., 1963. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters: Hugh-Jones - R.J. Bunche; Lord Caradon - R.J. Bunche., 1965 1969. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sampler., [Boxes 3-4, 11 folders]
  - Notes, 9., 1949-198. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Random selection of R.J. Bunche notes., June-December 1949. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Note: R.J. Bunche's religion. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Handwritten notes on R.J. Bunche's advice to youth, speech making methods, list of books on negroes in University of Minnesota, security in marriage. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - R.J. Bunche notes: teaching as a preference, interview w/Jane Taylor., 1989. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Excerpts from Blue Notebook. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Childhood., 1927-1970. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - R.J. Bunche's My Most Unforgettable Character & My Happiest Childhood Memory., 1954. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letters - R.J. Bunche to: E.M. Riley (), V.J. Betts; H. Salter (); M. Selby (); R.W. Hosie (); R. Taylor (); D. Rieber (); J.Phillips (); V.Kelley ()., 1956 1956 1968 1966 1969 1927 1956 1970. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - R.J. Bunche's anecdotes. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes: circus; jobs; childhood music; scholarship; Reed & Whitman Colleges (); UCLA commencement; Bunche Hall, UCLA. Speech: Young Negro., 1966 1926 or 1927. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Family., 1946-1968. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Verse on Mrs. Einstein's funeral ()., 1967. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notes: written on R.J. Bunche's father (); Letter: A.W. Bunch ()., 1962 1969. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Diary transcript:., 1946-1952, 1955, 1956, 1960, 1962, 1968. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Race., 1945-1969. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes: Christmas (); children; memory development; R.J. Bunche racial consciousness; notes; R.J. Bunche's diary., 1970 1945 July 7, 1938. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letters: R.J. Bunche to: W.E. Johnson (); M.W. Butler (); M. Greenwood (); G.M. Adams (); Gallagher & Goldberg ()., 1955 1960 1966 1969 1968. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Excerpts from R.J. Bunche speeches., 1954; 1956; 1962. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - R.J. Bunche's Race in World Perspective, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes: R.J. Bunche's experiences with prejudice/discrimination. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letters: D. Rusk - Urquhart (); R.J. Bunche - W. Eves () & P. Frederick (); Shifflett ()., 1981 1946 1969 1969. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Politics - United Nations., 1953-1969. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters: R.J. Bunche to: V.J. Betts (); Sam Souki (); Mrs. G.E. Hill (); F.E. Walser (); J.M. Wellman (); H.E. Lestmann (); M. Power; E. Gwynn Jones (); C. Fisher (); B.J. Johnson (); P.F. Hartunian ()., 1968, 1963, 1965 1949 1953 1955 1963 1963 1964 1967 1964 1970. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters: R.J. Bunche to: Y. Langton (); Morehouse (); P.A. Knox (); Conroy (); Smith (); W.G. Parker-B.E. Urquhart ()., 1968 1966 1968 1957 1969 1967. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notes: UN Atmosphere; Typescript (); press headlines ()., 1967, 1969, 1963 1959; 1966; 1967. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Minutes: Committee of., July 1968. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters - R.J. Bunche to: C. Bowles; C.Thompson; V.J. Betts., 1954 1963 1964. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Press clippings: Cleveland Plain Dealer,; New York Times., 1960 1984. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notes re UNEFCO Conference., 1966. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Philosophy., 1940-1970, bulk. (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Letters - R.J. Bunche to: D. Stern; J.C. Frantz; Buchanan; G.M. Adams; Students of Providence College (); C. Yeomans; L.V. Fulton (); Mrs. F.M. Roberts (); C.M. Pierce; M. McPherson ()., (1952) (1968) (1970) (1969) 1970 (1955) 1965 1965 (1959) 1949. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters - R.J. Bunche to: H. Gardner (); A.G. Draper III (); M.W. Butler (); Students of Sulpher High School ()., 1959 1961 1960 1967. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - List press clippings., 1959 and 1969. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Notes: Pugwash Conference; personal philosophy; leadership., 1969 1970 1949. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Interview: P. Frederick., 1969. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Notes: R.J. Bunche's personal philosophy., 1970, 1967, 1966, 1940, 1941, 1950, 1957. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters: R.J. Bunche to: W.E. Pereira (); Professor W.L. Dunn (); R. Ginzburg (); H. Gardner (); S.B. DeForest (); Cooke ()., 1970 1970 1953 1959 1957 1956. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Article: R.J. Bunche's What do you mean by happiness? & The Road to Peace. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Written letter to Jane from R.J. Bunche., 1962. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letter: R.J. Bunche & J.W. Coulter (); V.J. Betts (); Mrs. M. Frank ()., 1961 1965 1969. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Speech: World Peace & Religion., 1963. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Persons admired., 1967-1970. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters: R.J. Bunche to: W.H. Bingham (); Professor A.S. Dil (); V.J. Betts (); E. Warren (); Students of Providence College (); R. Vahl (); W. Riley and K. Ward ()., 1967 1967 1968, 1969 1969 1970 1970 1970. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Notes: love of nature., 1969, 1968, 1966. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters and notes concerning: Music, favorite verse, favorite sayings, favorite books, favorite musicals and movies, and hobbies., 1966-1970. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Habits., 1950-1968. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Letters and notes concerning smoking, anecdotes, humor, miscellaneous, and personal appearances., 1950-1968. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sports and health., 1922-1971. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes and letters on smoking; sports; health (); first meeting of R.J. Bunche and Ruth Harris., 1922-27 1928. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - R.J. Bunche's Recollections of a Sports Buff. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes, documents, cables, letters on R.J. Bunche's health. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - New York Times Index of R.J. Bunche's press clippings., 1968-1971. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- General Assembly, London, Trusteeship., 1946-1947.; [Box 4, 3 folders]
  - Papers about R.J. Bunche by L.S. Finkelstein. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Notes on First General Assembly Meeting. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fourth Committee Trusteeship and journal records of General Assembly., January-February 1946. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - R.J. Bunche's Fundamental Freedoms and Non-self Governing Peoples. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - International Labor Office memorandum from Canada., 1946. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Papers re U.S. & Non-self governing territories under the U.N.; functions of SPA; International trusteeship & accountability; trusteeship and dependent territories. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - R.J. Bunche notes., 1947. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters on race; R.J. Bunche notes on work of the trusteeship council. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - R.J. Bunche reports to V. Hoo and T. Lie., 1947. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Rules of Procedure for the Trusteeship Council, a background survey prepared by the Secretariat., September 1951.; Typescript (carbon) (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Palestine 1., 1914-1946; 1947.; [Box 5, 2 folders]
  - Middle East Developments., 1200s-November 1947. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts from Keesing's on Palestine., 1946-1947. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - List R.J. Bunche's professional employment., 1945-1955. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - R.J. Bunche's notes., 1947: January-December. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - R.J. Bunche's notes on United Nations Special Committee on Palestine., June-September 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - List United Nations Special Committee on Palestine public hearings/private meetings. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Keesing's on Palestine., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - List of speeches/visits by Heads of State, Dignitaries., 1945-1964. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - UN General Assembly notes., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Yearbook of the UN excerpts., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Analysis by Ad Hoc Committee on Palestinian Question., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New York Times Index on Palestine., 1947. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Index to Security Council, UN., 1946-1949. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Palestine 2., January-June 1948.; [Boxes 5-6, 5 folders]
  - Written notecards and excerpts from To Jerusalem. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Documents on foreign policy of Israel. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - R.J. Bunche's notes on Palestine., January-September 1948.; Typescript (carbon) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - List of R.J. Bunche's flight log., May-September 1948. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Draft of Mediator's Mission no.2-5,7. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Extracts from McCabe's cable, letter. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - P.C. Jessup statement to General Assembly. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Contacts by Cordier. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Security Council's resolution of Palestinian question. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - B.E. Urquhart Notes on notecards ()., March 5-May 10, 13-29, 1948. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - List R.J. Bunche photos., 1948. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Bunche Calendar notes., January-December 1948. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Keesing's outline of Mediator's 1st Progress Report re refugees., January, April, May 1948. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Truce Commission., January-December 1948. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - R.J. Bunche written notes June 30, on conferences - Shertok Haifa., June 1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - B.E. Urquhart notes., May 29-June 29, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Jerusalem., June 24, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Record of conversations R.J. Bunche & Cordier., June 7,9-11,15-17,20,29-30, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mediator's Mission no.8., June 1, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Security Council Yearbook., 1947-1948. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Report on the Supervision of the First Truce., January 29, 1949. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lecture by R.J. Bunche on Palestine., June 16, 1949. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Notes, papers on Count Folke Bernadotte., June 11, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Letter Cebe-Habersky-Beirut & R.J. Bunche., June 25, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Progress Report of UN Mediator on Palestine., May 14, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - B.E. Urquhart Notes., June 29-December 2, 1948. (Box 6, Folder 2)